Finding Aid for Philip E. Converse (1928-) Papers 1948-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Conferences, Professional Associations and Committees
  - Professional Associations and Committees (Box 9)
    - American Sociological Association 1977-1988 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Contributions of Behavioral and Social Science to the Prevention of Nuclear War 1986 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Professional Associations on Federal Statistics 1979-1981 (Box 9)
    - Consortium of Social Science Associations 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Council for Correspondence 1963 (Box 9)
    - Economic Dinner Group 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - International Political Science Association 1982-1987, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - National Academy of Sciences 1977-1989 (Box 9)
    - National Academy of Sciences-National Research Council 1966-1982, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities 1984-1985 (Box 9)
    - National Institute of Mental Health 1982-1987 (Box 9)
    - Research Doctorate Evaluation Committee 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Social Science Research Council Committees 1964-1967 (Box 9)
    - Social Science Research Council Presidential Search 1985 (Box 9)
    - Survey of Income and Program Participation 1982-1984 (Box 9)
    - Visiting Committee, Stanford Center for the Study of Youth Development 1986 (Box 9)
- Administrative Files
  Administrative Files (2 linear feet) reflect the administrative side of Converse's career. The series is divided into two sub-series: University Committees and Institute for Social Research. The sub-series University Committees is arranged alphabetically and documents membership in various university administrative committees and councils, primarily from 1985 to 1988. The majority of materials concern the Classified Research Committee. The Institute for Social Research sub-series is arranged alphabetically and covers the years 1963 to 1989. It broadly documents Converse's duties as director, and includes important reports from the 1986 visiting committee which was headed by James Tobin and reviewed ISR operations, and financial and budgetary materials. Also included are files from the institute's various component groups with which Converse was closely associated: the Center for Political Studies, the Survey Research Center, and the Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research.
  - University Committees
    - Academic Affairs Advisory Council 1986 (Box 10)
    - Academic Policy Group (APG) 1987 (Box 10)
    - Black Matters Committee 1974 (re: alleged racism in the Political Science Department) (Box 10)
    - Classified Research Committee 1985-1987, 10 folders (Box 10)
    - College Executive Committee 1987 (Box 10)
    - Committee on Data Collection Capabilities, Report of 1988 (Box 10)
    - Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award Committee 1986-1987 (Box 10)
    - Research Associates Dean Meeting 1988 (Box 10)
    - Scientific Club 1987 (Box 10)
  - Institute for Social Research
    - Administrative Committee 1982-1984 (Box 10)
      (includes materials re: Black Studies budget overrun)
    - Center for Political Studies
      - General 1980-1986 (Box 10)
      - Overhead Review Committee 1981 (Box 10)
    - "Cloyd Affair" 1988 (complaint lodged against ISR by Professor Emily Cloyd) (Box 10)
    - Cyclical Phenomena Program 1979 (Box 10)
    - Executive Committee, (1978-1987) (Box 10)
    - Financial
      - Annual Report of Financial Operations 1985-1987 (Box 10)
      - Comparative Statement of Financial Position 1980-1981 (Box 10)
      - Revenue Forecasting System 1986-1989 (Box 10)
      - Salaries 1986-1988 (Box 10)
      - Statements December 1975 (Box 10)
    - Inter-University Consortium for Political Research
      - Inventory of Data Resources 1963 (Box 10)
      - Organizational Structure, Location and Resources of ICPSR 1980 (Box 10)
    - LSA/ISR Joint Recruitment Fund 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - LSA/ISR Superfund 1986-1989, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - New Wing Addition 1984-1987 (Box 11)
    - Report of Recent Activities 1980 (Box 11)
    - Schedule of projects 1964 (Box 11)
    - Social Accounting (Tom Juster Proposal) 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Strategic Retreat 1988, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Survey Research Center
      - Cost Sharing with CPS 1983 (Box 11)
      - Survey Research Center Space Use 1986 (Box 11)
    - Threatt, Barbara (re: Breast Cancer Demonstration Project Records) 1986-1987 (Box 11)
    - Visiting Committee
      - "Tobin Report" 1986 (Box 11)
    - Response to "Tobin Report" 1986-1987, 3 folders (Box 11)
- Grants and Proposals 1962-1987, 1 linear feet
  Grant Proposals (1 linear foot) consists of reports and proposals submitted for grant funding, usually to the National Science Foundation. They are arranged chronologically and span 1962-1987. Most reports include summaries of research as well as general statements supporting the merits of the proposed research. Itemized budgets and researcher profiles complete the reports. In some instances evaluations of the proposals by outside reviewers are included. (It should be noted that many of the proposals were joint efforts involving contributions from multiple faculty members, some of which involved Converse only minimally.) This series also includes several of Converse's reviews of proposals submitted by researchers at other institutions. His reviews provide criticism and evaluation along with recommendations as to whether to approve funding. The file containing the reviews is listed at the end of the series. It is closed pending review of applicable laws.
  - 1962
    - "Continuing Study of Social Change" (NSF) 1962-1968 (Box 11)
  - 1966
    - "Proposal for Comparative Research" (Ford Foundation) (Box 11)
  - 1967
    - "Comparative Analysis of Multi-Nation Time Use Data" (NSF) (Box 11)
    - "Toward the Understanding of Social-Psychological Change in American Society" (Russell Sage Foundation) (Box 11)
  - 1969
    - "A Pilot Study of the Structure of Gratification" (Russell Sage Foundation) (Box 11)
  - 1970
    - "Indicators of Changes in People's Goals, Opportunities, and Economic Well-Being" (NSF) (Bernard Strumpel Proposal) (Box 11)
    - "Measuring the Quality of Life" (Russell Sage Foundation) (Box 11)
  - 1971
    - "Measuring the Quality of an Urban Environment" (NSF) (Roy Kaplan Proposal) (Box 11)
  - 1974
    - "Political Representation in an Authoritarian Regime" (Brazilian Study) (NSF) (Box 11)
  - 1975
    - "Public Policy and Public Opinion in Brazil" (Tinker Foundation) (Box 11)
  - 1976
    - "The Quality of Life as Perceived by Western Republics" (NSF) (Ronald Inglehart Proposal) (Box 11)
    - "Dynamics of Political Attitudes" (NSF) (Box 11)
  - 1977
    - "Changes in the Sense of Well-Being" (NSF), 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "Changes in the Sense of Well-Being" (National Institute of Mental Health) (Box 11)
  - 1979
    - "Dynamics of Subject Indicators of Life Quality" (NSF) (Box 11)
  - 1981
    - "Social Support and Psychological Well-Being" 1981-1983 (Box 11)
      National Institute of Aging) (Angus Campbell Proposal)
    - "Travel Grant Requests for Mannheim Conference" (NSF) (Box 11)
  - 1984
    - "Monitoring the Sense of Well-Being" (Box 11)
      (NSF, note: includes vita and writings)
    - "Monitoring the Sense of Well-Being" (proposal evaluations) (Box 11)
  - 1985
    - "Enlarging A Theory of Partisanship" (NSF) (Box 11)
    - "The Intersection of Personal and National History" (NSF) (Box 11)
  - 1987
    - "Presidential Selection in the U.S. and France" (NSF) (Box 11)
  - Proposals, reviewed by Philip Converse 1963-1986 (Box 12)
    [RESTRICTED closed pending review of applicable laws]
- Photographs, 1 folders
  Photographs, (one folder) consists of three photographs: one black and white group image of the participants in the "Political Issues and Business in 1964" conference (includes Philip Converse and Angus Campbell), and two color snapshots from a 1988 ICPSR committee meeting.
  - "Political Issues and Business Seminar," 1964 (Box 11)
  - ICPSR Council 1988 (Box 11)
- Closed Files, 12 folders
  Closed Files (12 folders) mostly concern faculty personnel matters. Due to their sensitive nature they are restricted for thirty years from the date of creation.
  - Arthur Miller Case 1977-1984, 9 folders (Box 12)
  - ISR Director Search, 1988 (Box 12)
    [RESTRICTED for 30 years from date of creation 2018 ]
  - Faculty Evaluations and Reviews 1969-1985 (Box 12)